Guide to the Luther Noss Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Luther Noss papers
1922-1995
MS 1853
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
49.92
(51 boxes)
Diaries, correspondence, subject files, photographs, publications, and printed material documenting the personal and professional lives of Luther Noss.
Noss, Luther, 1907-1995
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Estate of Osea Noss, 2005; transfer from the Irving S. Gilmore Music Library, 2012-2013.
Biographical / Historical
Luther Melancthon Noss was born on July 21, 1907, in Leland, Illinois. He was educated at Northwestern University (B. Mus., 1930) and Yale University (B. Mus., 1931, M. Mus., 1932). He served as a combat intelligence specialist with the 73rd Bombardment Wing during World War II, based in Saipan. He was assistant professor of music at Cornell University from 1935-1939; thereafter he spent the rest of his career at Yale University. He served as professor of music, chair of the department of music, dean of the school of music, director of the university choir, and master of Silliman College. He edited several hymnals and authored two books on the Yale School of Music and Paul Hindemith. In 1936 he married Osea Calciolari. Luther Noss died on February 9, 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Diaries, correspondence, subject files, photographs, publications, sheet music, and other printed material documenting the personal and professional lives of Luther Noss.
Noss, Luther, 1907-1995; Silliman College (Yale University); Yale School of Music; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Personal effects [includes desk items, jewelry, inkwell] (Box 1)
  - Personal effects [includes desk items, jewelry, inkwell] (Box 14)
  - Diaries/journals
    - 1923-1925, 1927-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1981 (Box 3)
    - 1982-1995 (Box 4)
    - Typed transcriptions of journals from 1927 to 1966 (Box 11)
  - Subject/correspondence files
    - A-E (Box 5)
    - F-M (Box 6)
    - N-R (Box 7)
    - S-Z, miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Hindemith book, draft (Box 9)
  - Yale University: course outlines for Choir Music and Liturgical Music (Box 10)
  - Noss family history and related materials (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 13)
  - Hymnology, psalm tunes, lecture outlines (Box 15)
  - Legal (Box 16)
  - Research files on church history, liturgy (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous personal papers (Box 18)
  - Yale University: School of Music, Silliman College (Box 19)
  - Books about Yale and School of Music (Box 20)
  - History of Yale (Box 21)
  - Travel [printed matter]
    - 1978-1984 (Box 22)
    - 1956-1963 (Box 23)
    - 1965-1971 (Box 24)
    - 1971-1976 (Box 25)
    - 1975-1977 (Box 26)
  - Travel journals (Box 27)
  - Photographs [family and Yale], Circa 1958-1984 (Box 28)
  - Photographs [family and Yale], Circa 1958-1984 (Box 30)
  - Photographs [family and Yale], Circa 1958-1984 (Box 31)
  - Early school and Europe photographs (Box 29)
  - Grade books, 1939-1953 (Box 31)
  - Photograph albums
    - 1922-1951 (Box 32)
    - 1922-1951 (Box 36)
    - 1952-1961 (Box 33)
    - 1960-1968 (Box 34)
    - 1969-1991 (Box 35)
  - Correspondence between Luther and Osea (Box 37)
  - Music theory texbook materials (Box 38)
  - Yale University: Battell Chapel bulletins (Box 39)
  - Photograph albums (Box 40)
  - Photograph albums (Box 41)
  - Photographs, diplomas, awards (Box 42)
- Additional Material, 1926-1995; Accession 2013-M-001
  Arrangement
  Materials in this accession are arranged according to document type. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically according to correspondent. Sheet music is arranged alphabetically according to the title of the composition.
  Scope and Contents
  This accession comprises concert programs; correspondence primarily pertaining to the publication of the book, Christian Hymns, edited by Luther Noss; research notes pertaining to Christian Hymns and to Noss's study of classical and liturgical music; papers written by Noss while a student at Northwestern University; and unpublished sheet music for compositions either written or arranged by Noss while a student at Northwestern University and the Yale School of Music, and as a professor at Cornell University.
  - Concert programs, 1938, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2-12)
  - Northwestern University: Student papers, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Research notes
    - Christian Hymns, 1955-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2-5)
    - Seminar on Bach, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
      - Oversize materials, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sheet music, A-O, 1927-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2-52)
  - Sheet music, P-W, 1926-1956 (Box 4, Folder 1-33)
- Additional Material, 1971-1990; Accession 2013-M-029
  This accession consists of office files from the 1970s related to Luther Noss' career as a professor at the Yale School of Music, as well as correspondence and subject files pertaining to the writing and publication of his book, Paul Hindemith in the United States.
  - Office files, 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Paul Hindemith in the United States
    - Correspondence, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Subject files
      - General, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Pre-1937, Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 1937 tour, Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - 1938 tour, Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - 1939 tour, Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Emigration, Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - 1940, Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - 1940-1953, Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Yale, Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Honors and recognition, Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - 1953-1959, Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - 1959-1964, Circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Additional Material, 1931-1974; Accession 2013-M-076
  This accession consists primarily of correspondence concerning Luther Noss's professional service and publications.
  - Catholic University of America, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Christian Hymns: correspondence, 1954-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Colby College, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hartt School, 1972, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hymnal for Colleges and Schools
    - Geer, E. Harold, correspondence, 1952-1956 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Notes, Circa 1952-circa 1956 (Box 2, Folder 4-6, Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - Prospectus, Circa 1954-circa 1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Suggestions, Circa 1952-circa 1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Tune data, 1953-circa 1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Indiana University School of Music, National Association of Schools of Music (NASM) evaluation, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Council of Churches correspondence
    - General, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The hymnal, Christian Hymns, 1954-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Northwestern University School of Music, National Association of Schools of Music (NASM) evaluation, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notes correspondence, 1948-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publications, Galaxy Music Corporation and Raymond A. Hoffman Company, 1931-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rice University Arts Advisory Council, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - University of West Florida, Pensacola, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)